The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help
MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high-quality
educational resources for free.
To make a donation or
view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses,
visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: So what I would
like to discuss today
is just touch upon
what kind of problems
the quantitative analysts
are solving in the commodity
world, the problems
that are somewhat
different from
the other markets.
And I'm sure you have the
whole year of lectures here
from people in
different markets.
And you will judge for yourself
that the models we're building
are somewhat, if not
completely, different.
So this is my goal
today is just for you
to have some taste of what kind
of models we're looking at.
So let's start.
Let's start with the following
abstract from the Dow Jones
publication, the
dispatch which announced
in 2009 that the Trafigura--
which is the biggest
trader, one of the biggest
commodity and energy trader--
is potentially on track to
post its best results ever
in fiscal 2009 on lower oil
prices and contango markets.
Remember, 2008, just the year
before that, the oil prices
shot to the highest possible
level, to $159 per barrel.
And a lot of people
blamed the traders
for the high oil prices.
And yet, in 2008, when the
prices dropped-- in 2009,
I'm sorry, next
year-- when the prices
dropped to $30 per barrel, as
you remember, to the lowest
possible level that
we remember, Trafigura
is about to make the
biggest profit ever.
So it sounds like
a contradiction.
So they're making money on the
low oil prices and contango.
And contango, which I have to
explain to you what it is-- I
assume that everybody here knows
what the futures contract is.
If not, just let me
know, and I will explain.
It's very simple concept, so
don't be shy and just tell me.
So I would like to
show you how Trafigura
will make the record
profit in the year
when the prices are at
the record low level,
but they are in contango.
So this is the graph
of futures contracts,
futures prices, oil futures
prices on January 15, 2009.
Futures contract is
simply the contract
that allows you to
buy today-- let's
say, in January--
the barrel of oil
for delivery in
some future time.
That's all.
You always know
what the price will
be by looking into Wall Street
Journal, Section C. Open,
you will see.
If you want to have
delivery in August,
the price will be around, what?
$55?
If you want delivery on February
of next year-- so February,
2010-- the price will be $60.
If you want delivery now,
the price will be $35.
So if you want to
buy, basically,
the spot price--
for your knowledge,
there is no spot price, as such.
And whatever you see on
CNBC, for example, on TV,
when they give you
the spot price of oil,
it's the price of the first
future contract-- so this one--
of the nearby, the most
nearby futures contract.
So as you can see,
this is the curve.
And recall that the curve is
in contango if the prices are
monotone increasing.
If they are decreasing,
it's called backwardation.
That's all.
So just a useful
term for you to know.
So at that time, January
15th, the prices indeed
were monotone increasing.
They're going from
$35 to February
and to $60 in February.
So this is February of 2009.
This is February of 2010.
And we can see the prices
were going from $35 to $60.
So let's now see how
Trafigura made money.
Can you guess, by the way?
Yes.
AUDIENCE: They borrowed
money, bought the spot
and then sold the
futures contract?
PROFESSOR: Exactly.
So that's precisely
what they've done.
What is needed for that, though?
There's one little
thing that's required.
AUDIENCE: Low interest rates
and ability to buy the spot?
PROFESSOR: This price
is the ability to buy.
But you need a little bit more.
You need--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: I'm sorry?
PROFESSOR: No, no, you lock in.
You bought at $35.
AUDIENCE: Storage.
PROFESSOR: Storage--
you need the storage.
You need to be able to wait one
year, because you already sold
at $60 next year, in February.
So you locked in
a massive profit
of-- so this is your strategy.
Just borrow 35.
Buy one barrel.
Store it.
Then immediately sell,
so short means just go
and sell the one barrel
for next year at $60.
So you have-- you
made $25-- I'm sorry,
you made $25 just on commodity.
You have to-- on February,
you will get this-- February
next year you will get this $25.
You'll pay the interest, which
will be maybe, let's say 10%.
So it will be $3.5.
So you made total profit $21.
If, like Trafigura, you have 50,
60 million barrels of storage,
you can easily
calculate how much money
they have without any risk they
made in this particular year.
So whenever you hear that
traders are benefiting
from the high prices, it's not.
Actually, if the same situations
existed in the high prices,
then the interest would
be substantially lower.
They could drop
their profit by 50%,
if, let's say, the same
where the prices $125
to $135 to $160.
Right?
You would have the
enormous interest payment.
So in reality, you
need the low prices,
but you would like
to have a contango.
You really don't care,
price is low or high.
So to summarize,
we need to have--
I mean, just a little thing
here-- that the strategy works
like a charm.
The only thing you
need is storage.
OK, let me now
invert the question.
Let me ask you this
question-- let's
say we have the same curve.
We are on January
1st, 2009, and we
are asked to get the storage.
You want to have your bosses
calling you and saying,
I mean, I need
storage, oil storage
from August to December.
So in August, we have the price
is, what, $55, in December $58.
You go and get me--
here's your credit card.
Just go and get it.
Well, storage is usually--
you get it at the auctions.
So a lot of people come to
the auction, and they'll bid.
So now you're going with the
boss's credit card, right?
And you have the
following dilemma--
if you borrow too little,
you will never get it.
If you bid too much, you'll have
the winner's curse-- namely,
you will never be able
to recover the money
that you paid for that storage.
So you have to have-- before you
bid, you have to have a plan.
How do you-- or strategy--
how do you recover the money
that you pay for the storage
through some foolproof,
riskless activity-- some
strategy like Trafigura.
Remember, they have
the riskless strategy.
They lock in the profit.
They can go to sleep for
a year, and then vacation,
and then come back and
get this profit back.
How do you-- in this
particular case, you have,
whenever you bid
something, you also
have to have a plan
in mind how to recover
this money and even more, to
get a little bit of profit.
So my question to you-- you
need storage from August
to December.
How much would you bid?
These are the prices.
If you need more prices,
they're all here.
So you need the storage
from August to December.
AUDIENCE: Do the same thing?
Do the same thing
they did before?
PROFESSOR: So how much would
you bid for the storage?
You don't have the storage, so
you have to-- when you get it,
then you do what we
did before, because
before what we did was assume
that we already have it.
Right now, you don't, but if
you win it, you will have it.
But if you win it, you
have to have the strategy
how to recover this money.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Depends on how
much profit you want to make.
PROFESSOR: Well, it's
not, because remember,
you are competing
against other people.
Right?
So if you become too greedy,
they will outbid you.
So let's say bid
one penny, right?
Assuming that you'll make--
so it should be-- what
is the highest you can bid?
AUDIENCE: $3?
PROFESSOR: Uh-huh.
You say $3.
All right, give me the
strategy that recovers that $3.
AUDIENCE: But we do
the same process.
We borrow money, buy--
PROFESSOR: You don't
have to borrow,
because it's futures contract.
You don't need-- you
just go long the August.
So buy August, using
the futures contract,
and sell December using
the futures contract.
You don't even need
to borrow money.
You will need to borrow, maybe,
when you get to August, right?
Then when you have to pay $55,
then you'll borrow, right?
So you bid $3, you recovered $3.
No profits.
So most likely, you
will bid $2.99, right?
That's the highest
probably, can go.
You have to give yourself at
least a penny of a profit,
right?
AUDIENCE: The interest.
PROFESSOR: I'm sorry?
AUDIENCE: Also the interest.
PROFESSOR: Let's forget
about interest for a moment,
just for simplicity.
In reality, of course, you
never should forget about it,
but in order not to make our
discussions too complicated,
no interest.
So you're basically will be at
$2.99, it seems to me, right?
You get a penny of profit,
and you have a strategy
if you get the storage.
You know what to do.
You immediately go buy August.
Using futures contract, buy
August, and sell December,
locking in $3.
Pay $2.99, if you manage
to win, if everybody is not
as smart as you
are, and just bid--
or maybe they want
bigger profit.
You will win the storage.
You will lock in.
OK, and everybody agrees, right?
This is actually a
standard strategy.
People use it all the time.
That's what I would
call-- that's what
the trader would do.
That's kind of the trader, so
a business guy would do that.
This is a common strategy--
was very, very common,
let's say in the '90s.
What the quant will
do-- and that's
where the added value of the
quant is to the organization--
they will do something
completely different.
What they will do-- they
will, on January 1st,
they will sell something that
is called August-December spread
option.
You heard the word
option, right?
Option is characterized by
the payout at expiration.
So we have expiration.
We have the payout.
This is not your typical
options, not like IBM option.
This is something different.
The payout is determined at
the expiration, which is,
let's say, July 31st, right
before the beginning of August,
right?
You will look again at
the Wall Street Journal
and look at the December and
August prices on July 31st.
And if the difference
is positive--
this little plus sign means
that if it's positive--
than you pay to the owner of
the option this difference.
If it's negative, you pay zero.
You're more familiar with the
options where one of this thing
is just a fixed strike.
It's called the fixed strike.
Here, there's no strike.
It simply the difference between
December and August contract.
But it's a
two-dimensional object,
so it's a little bit more
complicated to value it.
But there is a whole methodology
developed, the same way
for the regular options.
This is for the spread options.
So the quant will sell this
spread option on August 1st.
Why is it better?
Well, first of all, we have
to discuss how much will I
get for this option?
When I sold it, I give it to
you just for you to be confident
that I'm not trying to deceive
you or anything like that.
You will get-- this
is the formula that
is used to compute the
value of that option.
And when I substituted all the
parameters that are necessary,
I get that the value
of the option is 447.
So I immediately, on
January 1st, got 447.
Everybody else is
going ready to bid $3.
I have in my pocket 447.
I can bid, let's say, 420.
Right?
Guaranteed if I know that
everybody else is bidding $30,
I will win the storage.
Plus my profit margin
is not a penny anymore.
My profit margin
is $0.27, right?
If I can do even 410, even
increase my profit margin
if I really want to be greedy
in this particular case.
But clearly, I can
have a bigger margin.
I can have a bigger-- you
can guess, by the way,
without even looking
at the formula, why
the value of this option
was the payout like this--
was this payout.
Why is it bigger than $3?
It's always bigger than $3.
AUDIENCE: Discount?
PROFESSOR: No, forget about,
again, interest rates.
It's not the discount.
What is the-- on January 1st,
what is the intrinsic value?
If there's no
volatility at all, then
the intrinsic value
of the options-- so
at zero volatility,
the value of the option
is exactly the difference
between December and August
on January 1st, which is $3.
So $3 is the intrinsic
value of that option.
And we all know that
the value of the option
is greater than the intrinsic
value if there is a volatility.
Because there is a volatility,
the value is greater than $3.
And actually, it's
substantially greater than $3,
because the volatility in the
energy markets is very high.
It's much, much
higher than what you
see in the interest rates, or FX
or equities-- indices, I mean.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: So you're
getting money
from taking on more
risk, basically?
PROFESSOR: Let's--
we'll get to that.
You are asking exactly
the correct question,
because yes, I am proud.
I got 447.
I paid 420.
I mean, I was bidding 420.
Of course I won.
I got my storage.
I bring it back home.
Now let's see what kind
of risk I brought home.
I have $0.27 in my pocket left.
That's my profit.
But now let's
assume on July 31st,
let's say December
price goes to $80
and the August
price goes to $55.
I sold this option.
How much do I owe on July
31st-- option is exercised.
How much do I owe to
the owner of the option
if December, on July
31st, 80 and August is 55?
Yes, $25.
I have only $0.27
in my pocket, right?
So what do I do?
That's my risk, as
you're telling me.
This is a risk that
all of a sudden,
I owe astronomical
amount of money
to the person to whom
I sold this option.
So what do I do?
Do I run to Venezuela or
what, I'm interested to know.
Where?
Can you guess?
Remember, I have storage.
And on July 31st, the
August price is $55,
and the December is $80.
So you already told me what
to do in this situation.
That's what traders would do.
They will buy immediately
the August at $55,
immediately sell December,
because I have the storage.
Now I can extract this $25
using my physical asset.
So this is the beauty of the
physical or real options--
that I can, by doing
certain things,
I can extract the
payout of the option.
So I'm completely protected.
So it seems to me that my
storage and that spread option
is the same thing.
Because I'm fully
hedged with my storage.
Right, is that clear?
Do you understand how I managed
to escape terrible predicament?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: What happens
when the value of what
you have in storage
falls greater than what
you received from the auction?
PROFESSOR: But it's
an auction, right?
So I received 447.
Everybody bids $3 or
$2.99 and then 420.
There's no value of the
storage, except for the value
what people are bidding for.
So if my bid is the
highest, that's it.
I received it.
So is that your question, or are
you asking me something else?
AUDIENCE: I want to
visualize the payoff.
It's when the--
PROFESSOR: Oh, you're
talking about what
happens if vice versa, December
not goes to $80, but to $20,
right?
And this one still
remains at $55.
I do nothing, because the payout
of the option is equal to zero,
because the difference
is negative.
So I owe nothing to the
owner of the option,
and I do nothing
with my storage.
It's a fully hedged proposition.
So the storage and this
option is one and the same.
OK?
Any questions?
So conceptually, we're
on the same page, right?
OK, so that was of
course of the caricature
of the real situation.
So reality is somewhat more
complicated, as always.
In reality, let's say I
go and bid for two years.
I need the storage
for two years.
There are many spread
options I can sell, right?
In this, my example-- again,
in the caricature example,
I sold August-December.
I could have sold
August-November,
August-October, right?
Or I can sell-- if I
have for two years,
I can say May, November,
June, September, and so on.
If I have two years, it's 24.
You can understand how
many options I can sell.
I mean, just options
where-- options
to put the oil into the
tank today, and extract it
six months later
with some profit,
or maybe three months later.
And so there are a
lot of these options.
So first of all I
have to determine--
so I can sell a lot of this
option against the storage.
I have to determine A: what
is the most valuable portfolio
of options I can sell
against the storage?
This is-- our strategy
starts shaping up.
So we want to
optimize something.
And what are we optimizing?
We're optimizing the
value of the portfolio
that we can sell
against the storage.
Value is-- remember
this cash that I
get from selling the option?
I want to get not just 447.
I want to get 447,000--
just whatever.
just I want to
maximize, and bring it
to the highest possible level
based on the information--
price information, volatility
information-- that exists
at this particular moment.
I want to determine what
kind of portfolio options.
Now, this is optimization.
What are the constraints?
And now the constraints
are requiring
that you have some technical,
contractual, legal,
and environmental understanding
of what's going on.
The simplest constraints I can
give you is that you cannot put
the gas in the ground or oil
in the tank as quickly as you
want.
There are certain constraints
on the injection rate.
on the withdrawal rate.
You cannot instantaneously
extract gas from the ground,
or oil from the tank.
You can never have a
situation-- remember
that whenever the
option expires,
you have to do
something to extract.
Remember, to extract the value,
whenever you owe somebody--
the option holder--
$15 or $25, you
have to put the oil in the tank,
wait six months, extract it.
Under no circumstances--
so your option portfolio
should be sold in such a
way against the storage
that under no circumstances,
you are in the situation when
the option is in the money.
So option is positive.
You have to do something
to extract the value.
So you have to inject,
and there's no space,
because you've done
something before,
because some other
options expired before,
and you put already
oil in the tank.
And the tank is full.
And now a new option
expires, and tells
you put more into the
tank, and there's no space.
In the opposite
situation, when you
need to sell from
the tank and the tank
is empty, because some other
options from that portfolio
managed to completely deplete
the oil from the tank.
Questions?
So let's try to make an attempt
to write this optimization
problem.
Just for fun, so that you
have an idea what's going on.
So first of all, let's see
what we're trying to optimize.
Let's start from the end.
This contract simply
tells me that I
wanted some particular-- F
is the price of the futures
contract with expiration,
let's say, the month of June.
So this particular
term of the sum
tells me that how
much I will have
to pay in June if I
buy-- this is the volume.
Let's say right now is January.
If I buy in June this amount of
oil using my futures contract,
how much I have to pay?
This is kind of
cash from my pocket.
Right?
I mean, it's clear.
The same thing here.
There is option here.
This is just straightforward
buying and selling,
buying into the storage and
selling from the storage.
Agreed?
A little bit more
complicated is this list.
This is the option as I told
you before-- the option that
injects oil into the
tank at one month,
and extract it in
month i, and extract it
in the month j, which is later.
So you extract in June,
extract in November.
So this is the
value of the option.
This is the volume
associated with this option.
I sold this option.
Therefore, I have the
positive cash flow.
So this is 447 in my pocket.
This is another
option that I sold.
This is an option which
is kind of opposite, which
is first you extract,
then you inject,
which is typical situation
when you receive your storage
with already oil in the tank.
The curve is not contango,
but backwardation.
So it's more profitable
for you to sell it now
because the prices are high,
and then replace it later.
So it's kind of symmetric
situation to this one,
to the options that
we already discussed.
It's just it works
when the curve is
in the opposite direction.
So you try to make
money no matter how.
Just the prices look.
You're trying to
make this money.
So you try to optimize
this portfolio.
OK?
Now, let's talk
about constraints.
To determine the constraints,
I introduce right now
the Boolean variable, which is
1 or 0, which basically tells
me if, when I come to the
exercise of this option--
like in our case on July
31st, in our first example--
and I see the option
is in the money or not.
So do I have to do
something or not?
Do I have to inject
into the storage?
And so is it $15
or it's minus $15?
If it's minus $15, the
difference between the prices,
I don't do anything.
So then it's 0.
If it's plus $15, I
have to do something,
because the owner of the
option asks me $15, right?
And so I have to put
oil into the tank,
and extract it sometime later.
So that's one.
The same thing with
the option which
is opposite-- first
withdrawal, then injection.
So then injection constraints
will be quite simple.
So at the expiration, I look.
If this one is 1, then it means
that I have to do something.
And what I have to do, I have
to inject-- at the month i,
I have to inject
this volume x_(i,j),
which was withdrawn later.
So that is injection.
If some option before
that was in the minus--
so I have to inject
before and withdraw now,
that will cancel my injection.
So if simultaneously,
I have injection,
because one option is in
the money, and withdrawal,
because the option that
was exercised before
is in the money, they
kind of cancel each other.
So that's why this
sign is plus and minus.
The same thing with others
options, and the same thing
with pure futures contract.
And that should be less
than the injection rate.
The same thing with
withdrawal rate, right?
I mean, it's a
similar consideration.
Now, maximum
capacity constraints,
it tells me that if I start
with this inventory in my tank
at time 0, and this
is basically how much
I will get at any
time i, for any month
i, that's how much I will have
in my tank by that time i.
You have to believe me, because
it's not a trivial thing.
But the same thing with
minimum constraints.
What you really
have to understand,
that unknowns are x, y,
z, v, and unfortunately,
omega is also unknown.
Omega is just-- it's basically
these are the volumes.
This is the kind of control
variable, the price.
And the price can be-- the
spread can be positive,
can be negative, can be 0.
And this is becoming a very
ugly, non-linear problem,
very quickly.
Very big, so you have
a lot of variables.
For two years, you have, what,
12 times 11, which is 132.
Let me just-- no, 24.
I'm sorry.
It's 24 times 23, so
it's 12 times-- so it's
a big number of
variables, plus an equally
big number of constraints, and
the constraints are non-linear.
So the problem is pretty hard.
I leave it up to you to
decide how to solve it.
That's why they take
optimization courses here.
I can suggest that there are
several approaches people
would take.
There's approximation, where
this problem is approximated,
let's say by linear programming,
or quadratic programming,
or whatever you want.
You can do it through
Monte-Carlo simulations.
Or there is an
interesting approach
through the stochastic control.
I recommend you a paper
by Carmona and Ludkovski,
exactly how to do this-- how
to make a decision of injecting
oil or withdrawing oil based
on the stochastic control,
stochastic optimization
methodology.
But it is quite an
interesting paper.
So either of these
approaches can be used.
And they are used, and give you
sometimes different results,
but you can look.
Any questions so far?
AUDIENCE: Is the
stochastic control solution
an optimal solution
or exact solution?
Is it giving the solution that
the Monte-Carlo simulation's
approximating?
PROFESSOR: Let me
put it this way.
None of these solutions
is better, or prettier,
or whatever, because
of the parameters
that go into the problem.
And you can have the
most precise methodology,
but if your parameters
are only 50%
accurate-- in reality,
all those parameters
necessarily for
Monte-Carlo simulations
with stochastic
control, we really
don't know what they are.
We can only can guess through
some implied market parameter
volatility, and so on.
And if you're
wrong, you're wrong.
Even your method can
be absolutely precise.
I like it, because it's really
very nice mathematics there.
We personally don't do that.
I'm not going to tell
you what we're using,
but we do something different.
And our methodology is
chosen to be robust.
We chose it because we
want the methodology
to be extremely robust.
So we don't want
small changes-- we
don't want to have
the situation where
small changes, which usually
comes when you overparametrize.
I mean, people like to go and
later-- in the second half--
I will discuss some of
the models people use.
For example, they
see the richness
of the behavior of
the prices, and they
want to introduce
a lot of parameters
to capture this richness.
By that, they sacrifice the
stability and robustness.
So little changes in the
parameters and the value
can change substantially.
So we prefer a
different approach,
where we maybe a sacrifice
some of the value,
but we will gain the
robustness, stability.
And this is the most
important thing.
And most importantly, everything
that we use in the model
can be verified by the outside
regulators and controllers,
which in this day and age
is extremely important.
Because these days,
to have a model that
is calibrated-- even
the word calibrated
causes a lot of
antennas just going up.
So we try not to
calibrate anything.
Everything that we
do can be verified--
every little brick that
goes into the model
can be traded in the
market, and can be verified.
This is very, very important
in this day and age.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
What do you mean by
calibration [INAUDIBLE]?
PROFESSOR: We'll get to
that, but very quick answer
is this-- just you have a lot
of parameters in the model.
I'll show some of the
models people use.
These parameters are not-- you
don't see them in the market.
It's the result of your model.
It's because you chose
this particular model.
Black-Scholes uses
one parameter.
If you use Black-Scholes
with jump-diffusion term,
and some other, you introduce
another ten parameters.
These parameters
are not observable,
so you have to somehow calibrate
it to some market data.
And the calibration becoming
a pretty interesting,
because calibration usually is
done through some kind of least
squares approach.
So you try to look at
the observable data,
and then adjust your parameters
using some least squares
approach to match that data.
Least squares is
notoriously bad-- problem,
so you may have many solutions.
The solution set
can be very flat,
so you can stop very early.
So there are problems
with least squares.
It's non-linear optimization, so
by itself, it's very difficult.
So calibration can be
very, very unstable.
Any more?
OK.
Now I have to tell
you the secret--
there is no Santa Claus.
Just remember, I was telling you
that I go and I sold the option
to get 447.
I've got the option.
In reality there is
no option market.
Nobody will buy this
option from you.
The market for this
option-- non-existent.
Now what do we do in this
particular situation?
That's where the whole beauty of
Black-Scholes comes into play.
Black-Scholes didn't
get the Nobel Prize
for integrating some very
simple payoff function that you
can do in first year of school.
They got the Nobel Prize-- or
they got kind of appreciation
for what they've done,
because they showed
that, with this value, they also
have the strategy that allows
you by doing something every
day or every half a day,
you can replicate this value.
So if you paid for
the option $5, then
you can show what
to do every day.
They tell you what to
do every day in order
to get back this $5 at the end.
So that's what their
main achievement.
Or if I sold an option,
and received $5,
then I will do
something that-- I
will use this $5 to replicate
any payout I owe at the end.
So I sold it to
you, for example.
So at the end, I owe you $50.
But they showed how,
through the dynamic hedging,
and using this $5 that
I receive up front,
I can be able to meet
my obligations to you.
So they showed how to replicate
the payout of the option.
So in reality, I don't
have to have the market.
If I sold somebody
an option for 47,
I don't have to have
anybody who buys it.
What I will do, I will simply
use this dynamic hedging
strategy that
Black-Scholes advised me,
adopt it to the spread
options, which at the end
will produce for me 447.
That's it.
But here again,
this is another task
that quants will have to do.
Not only they will
find the value.
They will produce every
day the strategy that
allows you to extract this 447.
So we already showed what
to do with the storage.
But now you have to do on
the next level of complexity.
You have to tell to the trader
what to do every day in order
to, in reality, get this 447
from selling this option.
So you told this trader,
I'm selling this portfolio
for $100,000 for the storage.
OK, so, but there's
nobody to sell it.
And you'll say, don't worry.
I will do it through
dynamic hedging.
At the end, you will
get your $100,000.
So he will believe you.
And then he will do it.
He will get $100,000.
Then, on the next level you
have to work with the guy who
operates the storage.
And you will tell the
person when to inject oil,
and when to withdraw, and to
get all of this magic which
we've discussed before.
So I think it'll be
a very logical point
for me right now to stop.
And in the next
half, we'll discuss
how to model the power plant.
So we're going to
the next topic.
So far, we have
covered how to model
a physical asset named storage.
The same approach can be used
to model practically everything
that we're interested in.
For example, we can
use the same thing
to model the tankers,
power plants, these storage
refineries, anything,
power lines, pipelines,
everything can be modeled
using this methodology.
Of course, the nature of
the beast will be different.
And you have to understand the
nuances and the-- as I said,
the constraints.
This modeling--
for example, tanker
requires understanding
of all the routes,
and the constraints in the
ports, and all these things.
But the conceptual philosophical
approach is the same.
You have to find
some optionality
and that's some
additional value.
So I obviously don't have time
to go over the whole thing.
But let's, again, for you
to have a taste of this,
let me just-- let's decide
how to model the power plant.
Assume that you are the manager
of the merchant power plant.
Merchant means that you decide
when to run it, or not run it.
You run it to maximize the
profit of this power plant.
So how do you decide?
Let's say you decide once
a day, in the morning,
whether to turn it on or turn
it off, or not to turn it on.
So how do you decide?
Well, sounds complicated.
In reality, it's very simple.
You wake up in the morning.
You look, first of
all, at the newspaper
and find out what's the
price of electricity today.
And price of electricity
you know for each hour--
sometimes for each 15 minutes.
It's determined.
So you know for each hour,
or maybe the daily price,
enough for the whole day.
So that's the price.
If you sell it, that's how
much money you will get.
On the other hand, to produce
one megawatt-hour of power,
you have to do something.
You have to turn
on your turbines.
So you have to bring some fuel.
You have to put some fuel into
the turbines, just to make them
move, and produce electricity.
Fuel can be anything.
Let's say it's natural
gas, but some fuel.
Now you have to
determine-- so you
know how much money you'll get
for one megawatt-hour of power,
right?
But how much it will
cost you to produce it?
So how much fuel you
need to determine
how much-- first of all,
how much it costs you
in terms of fuel to produce
this one megawatt-hour,
you have to know the
efficiency of the plant.
Because efficiency of
the plant is telling you
how much units of fuel--
let's say how much MmBTUs,
so millions British thermal
units of natural gas, that's
how it's measured-- how
much MmBTUs of natural gas
you have to burn to
produce one megawatt-hour.
Well, this measure of
efficiency for the power plant
is something called heat rate.
So heat rate is exactly
this coefficient
by which you multiply the-- so
if I say that heat rate is 7,
it means that I need 7
MmBTUs of natural gas
to produce one megawatt-hour
of power-- that's all.
So in our case, there's
nothing to be concerned about.
It's just simply some
constant that is given.
It's some constant
between 7 to 20.
20 is a very inefficient
plant, very rarely run.
Seven is right now more
kind of a standard constant.
That's the constant
corresponding
to the natural gas
power plant, which
is-- right now the majority
of the new plants is
the natural gas plants.
And there are some
other costs associated
with producing one
megawatt-hour-- just
air-conditioning, labor
costs, and so on and so forth.
Typically, they are not
the biggest component.
So if, let's say,
this is seven, what
is the price of
natural gas right now?
Do you remember?
AUDIENCE: $3.20.
PROFESSOR: That's--
I wish, but it's not.
It's around $4 right now,
let's say, per MmBTU.
So you need $28.
This is probably around
$3, so you need $31
to produce one megawatt-hour.
AUDIENCE: I was
thinking of gasoline.
PROFESSOR: Oh, no, not
that gas-- natural gas.
Sorry about that, but
just even gasoline
is right now around $5.
AUDIENCE: Really?
PROFESSOR: Yes.
Or maybe you are filling
your tank someplace
which you'll share with us.
[LAUGHS] So is that clear?
That's basically--
so you wake up.
You look at the
price of the power.
Let's say it's $50.
You know your plant is,
let's say, heat rate 8.
You look at the
price of natural gas.
It's $4, variable cost $3.
Will we run the plant?
What will be your profit?
So $4, 8, 3, so it's
$35 it will cost you
to produce one megawatt-hour.
This is $50.
You made $15 profit.
You turn it on.
It runs.
If, on the other hand,
the price of power
will be $30-- you look
in the newspaper--
you go back to sleep.
And nothing happens.
You get zero for that day.
So this is the maximum
between this price and zero.
Agreed?
Well now, before I
go to the next slide,
I have to-- together, we'll
have to determine what
is-- if I want to buy a plant--
if I want to buy a power plant,
how much I'm willing
to pay for that.
Well what I'm willing to pay--
I know that every day I'm
getting this thing, right?
But I don't know.
Each of these things
is a random number.
So I have to kind
of buy-- I have
to construct the
distribution of this price,
of this price, maybe
correlation between them.
It's a two-dimensional
distribution, so correlation,
find some expected value.
And that's how much I will want
to pay for the power plant.
So now we come to an
interesting question.
So now, real work starts.
So I know that this is the
value that I have to integrate,
but I don't know with respect
to which distribution.
So I have to now construct the
model of the power prices, fuel
prices.
And then take this
two-dimensional distribution
and try to find the expectation.
And that's how much
I'm willing to pay
for this power plant-- agreed?
Well, so let's start with kind
of building these components.
That's what, again,
quants will do
using already the experience
from other markets, and so on.
You already heard
the other lectures.
So what we'll do, we'll first
look at the distribution
of power prices to see.
Because I don't
know how to model
the evolution of power prices.
I know if I use simply
Brownian motion-- let's
say it's my first idea.
Well, let's see.
Brownian motion gives
us the distribution
which is, as you remember,
at any point of time is
kind of normally distributed.
If I look at the terminal
distribution of price, which
is driven by Brownian motion--
if I assume that the price is
driven by Brownian
motion, then at the end,
I'll get the normal
distribution.
So if I look at the, say
equity-- this is S&P 500--
indeed it's-- we all know
that S&P has fat tails, right?
But as we can see in a moment,
this is not a fat tail.
This is very close to
the normal distribution.
For the equity guys,
of course, for the guys
who trade the stocks, it's
an enormously fat tail.
But from the commodity
point of view,
this is just perfect,
normal distribution.
This is the distribution
that we deal with.
This is-- the tails
here are just-- so
the normal distribution just
out of the window immediately.
So Brownian motion
out of the window--
we cannot construct this
distribution of the terminal
prices of power using that.
That's one thing.
So we have very fat tails.
And this is the kind
of the parameters
that specify the distribution.
If I look at the, let's
say the equity index,
the kurtosis is very
close to the kurtosis
of the normal distribution,
which is 3 exactly.
But if I look at
the Nord Pool, which
is the power prices in
Scandinavian countries,
kurtosis is 26.
If I look at the
one-hour price, it's 76.
So it is, as you can see, as
far from normal as possible.
And we've seen it
in the picture.
And these are the numbers
corresponding to that.
Moreover, look at the
behavior of the prices.
This is the price in Texas, for
example, power prices in Texas.
What immediately jumps-- I
mean, look at the prices,
and say, wow, how is
it different from what
you see, let's say, in the
equity world, the stock market,
for example?
What is it that
immediately jumps at you?
What is different here?
Go ahead.
There's no right
or wrong answer.
AUDIENCE: Spikes.
PROFESSOR: Spikes--
that's the key word.
Like no other market,
we have spikes here.
That's a major,
major issue for us
from the modeling point of view.
You take any standard,
say Brownian motion,
it will never
exhibit the spikes.
Not only that, the
volatility, of course,
of the prices, as we
already expect, is huge.
It's hundreds.
S&P volatility right
now is 10% percent.
This is 100, 200,
sometimes 1,000, right?
All the intuition you
have about the behavior
of the prices, the behavior
of the random variables,
is mostly evolved,
all this intuition,
under this 10, 15, 20%
volatility assumption.
When the variables behave in
a completely different way
when they have volatility
of 100% or 200% or 300%,
so that's another thing that
will be challenging us, spikes
and high volatility.
It's just the same thing.
It's everywhere,
so I just wanted
to bring-- a different
region of the country,
it will be exactly
the same thing.
So it's common thing.
So if you look, and start
to summarize what we're
trying to capture
is-- mean reversion
and spikes are more or
less the same thing,
so we know if we go far
away, it will go back--
high kurtosis,
regime switching, I
will talk about that in a
moment-- and non-stationarity.
That goes without saying.
That's true for
most of the markets.
And now the problem that
we have to capture--
or not the problem
but another phenomenon
that we have to capture--
that the power and the fuel,
natural gas, exhibit a
very particular structure
of the correlation.
So correlation is not a number.
It's dependent the heat
rate in the market.
Remember heat rate is the
efficiency of the power plant
that are running in the market.
Depending on the efficiency, you
may have very high correlation
or low correlation.
We'll discuss that at the
end of this talk, which
is why this here.
Right now, I'm giving you
something that we observe,
and our models, preferably,
should capture that as well.
So requirements for our
model are pretty intense,
and pretty difficult. I
don't think that you ever
assume the requirement
of the correlation
should have some particular
structure, just depending
on some parameters, and so on.
OK, any questions?
So the models typically--
the first thing people do,
they take the models that they
know, and they try to apply.
Let's just very quickly
go through the models.
I mean, you've seen
these models already
in the previous lectures, right?
Let's start with the
straightforward geometric
Brownian motion, which out of
the window right away, right?
I mean you agree, because
no spikes, no high--
no correlation
structure, nothing.
So it's clear that in order
to-- we want to kind of start
with Brownian motion,
geometric Brownian motion,
try to maybe modify
it a little bit.
So what is spike?
Spike means that
just things go up,
and then they're pulled back.
So there should be some
mean reversion, right?
So mean reversion
is good, right?
But unfortunately,
mean reversion,
if you-- first of all, it's
pretty strong, so it goes,
remember, if the price
goes from $30 to $1,000,
and go back to $30,
mean reversion should
be extremely strong, right?
Second of all, what pushes
it to the $1,000 level?
You need to have a jump.
So that's why people
introduce the jumps.
So we have mean
reversion, jumps; jumps
and mean reversion.
Still it is becoming
pretty clear
that this will not work
for the following reason:
it goes from $30
to $1,000, and then
it goes back,
because it's a spike.
It goes back within
three or four days.
It comes back.
So the mean reversion
should be extremely strong.
The force of pulling back
But if it's so strong
that it moves you back
from $1,000 to $30,
imagine what it does when
you're on the level of $30.
Because it will be completely
flat-- just nothing,
you could not move there, right?
So people observed that,
and introduced, well, they
figured out maybe
the mean reversion
will be different at
the level of $1,000
than when you are at
the normal level of $30,
so the difference.
So you introduce right now
so-called regime switching.
So it means that
all the parameters
change, so you introduce
the kind of the high price
level, low price level,
parameters change.
And now we're getting
to the example
that we discussed
in the first half.
You end up with the
model with 10 parameters,
12 parameters, which is
absolutely impossible
to manage.
I mean, I can give
you another, probably,
hour discussing why
this approach in general
is not good.
And not just in commodities,
but everywhere else.
I mean, I'm not a big fan of
making the models extremely
complicated, because
introduction of one complexity
leads to introduction
of another complexity.
And you just cannot
manage this thing.
It's impossible to manage.
Theoretically, it looks
fantastic-- unmanageable.
So we have to figure
out something else.
So all these
methodologies-- and I
put them there-- the
methodologies people actually
use, the stochastic volatility,
the regime switching,
multiple jumps, and so on.
This-- it's all used, but it's
not what I want to suggest.
I want to suggest something
completely different.
These are the methodologies
that typically
are coming from fixed-income
world or foreign exchange
or equities and so on.
I want to introduce something
completely different.
Any questions so far?
So I want to introduce
the methodology which
is more suitable and
more understandable from
the commodity point of view.
Because actually, what's
the price of commodity?
Price of commodity is
driven by only two things.
Can you guess which?
AUDIENCE: Supply and demand.
PROFESSOR: Exactly, supply
and demand-- that's all it is.
That's what we'll try to do.
Maybe we can-- we have a hard
time modeling the commodity
prices using just these
standard methodologies
from different markets,
which rely only on the prices
themselves.
Maybe if I introduce some
fundamental modeling as well,
I can do it without losing
the most important part
of this model, is it
matches the market data.
So I have to-- A: I want
to model supply and demand.
But I also would like to match
every market data that I have.
So maybe I introduce
a completely different
complexity, maybe not.
So let's try to see if I
can succeed here or not.
Before we're going to go
into the depths of this,
let's discuss how the
power prices are formed.
Power prices are formed
in the following way--
let's say that the market
consists of two power plants.
And there's Generator
One and Generator Two.
Every day, they get prices of
power formed at the auction.
So every time the
generators will
submit the bids, which says
the following-- I can generate
50 megawatt for a given hour.
I will generate 50 megawatt.
If you ask me only
to generate 50,
I will generate them at $20.
Why?
Because I will run my most
efficient power plant,
which is the
cheapest one to run.
I will generate 50 megawatts.
If you want more, if
you want me to-- I'm
bidding-- if you
want me to do 100,
then you'll have to
pay me $25, because I
will have to introduce less
efficient power plants,
and so on.
200 to $30, and if you
want me to me generate 600,
you will have to pay me $50.
So that's my bid,
so-called bid stack.
That's what I'm
sending to the auction.
The other guy is
sending similar things.
The auctioneer-- there
is an auctioneer,
organization called independent
system operator, ISO.
They collect all these bids.
They know what demand
will be tomorrow.
They collect, and then
knowing this demand,
they will-- first of all, they
will sort out all the bids
in the most optimal way.
So they'll put it all
together by sorting.
So this is the auctioneer
combined all these two
bids, created this
graph-- so basically based
on how much they
need to generate.
So based on the demand,
this will be the price.
That will be the clearing
price of the market.
And then, because the
auctioneer knows all the bids,
the auctioneer will
send the demand
for this generator
and that generator.
So you will generate 60, you
will generate 600, or whatever.
The final price is the highest,
basically highest price
that is necessary
to meet the demand.
So if the demand is 600,
so this will be the price.
If it's 800, this
will be the price.
So the price is
clearly the function
of demand for any given day.
Well, even if this
is the case, then
if I look at the-- if I plot,
do the scatter-plot demand
versus price, I'll have
to see something similar.
Well, let's see.
When we take a
particular market,
and do the scattered graph,
so demand versus the price,
you see this is the graph
that we expect to see.
It's a little bit fat.
Why is it fat?
Why is it not a straight line?
Why is it not the line
as before, but it's fat?
What is random here?
Remember I told you
that each generator will
bid approximately how much
it will cost them to generate
at the particular day.
That cost depends
on the fuel price,
and that is a random number.
So what you can see here
is a lot of these curves,
but they are kind of randomly
moving because of the fuel
price affects the
cost of running.
But conceptually,
philosophically, this
is exactly what we discussed--
that these guys will
bid this curve.
And depending on the
demand, the price
will be simply the
value on that curve.
Are you with me?
So far so good?
So this is-- that's what
we're trying to model.
So if we can model that, if
I can model for every day
the bid curve that
the auctioneer,
the independent
system operator, sees,
I know the price at
that particular day.
Moreover, I don't want
to get too complicated,
but in reality,
I don't even have
to know precisely the curve.
I kind of have to know
precisely the distribution,
because remember, for
the value of the option,
you don't need to know where
the price will be at expiration.
You just need to know how the
price will be distributed.
If you catch the
distribution correctly
through, again,
dynamic hedging and so
on-- that's what
Black-Scholes tells you--
you can actually value
the option correctly.
So you can value the
power plant correctly.
But that's besides the point.
The point is right now
I'm trying to model,
somehow, the randomness
of this bid curve.
So now, to summarize, the power
price is the function of what?
Of demand, clearly-- we
already know it is that.
But also the fuel
prices, because the fuel
prices determine the
cost of generation
and therefore, how much
each generator will
bid into the market.
That's dependent on the cost.
If the natural gas
goes through the roof,
the price of generating one
megawatt will be very high.
So the person will
be-- the generator
will be bidding
very high prices.
And that's what we see here.
And also outages-- we
have to model outages,
because the market
is only finite, kind
of fleet of the power plants.
And if a couple of them will
go down, the price of power
can be affected dramatically.
The 1997, the Indiana-- the
price went from $40 to $7,000
because tornado hit
the nuclear plant.
You take a big chunk of the
generation from the stack,
and all of a sudden,
you have to run
absolutely anything, including
some very expensive diesels,
and so on.
So the price of power,
obviously, goes very high.
OK, so these are three
things that we try to model.
So how will we model that?
Well, before even I get
to the modeling of them,
let me just again outline
our modeling approach.
If I know the fuel-- let's say
there are no outages-- if I
know the fuel price,
I know then how much
each of the
generators-- how much
it will cost for each of the
generators in the market.
Because I know
everybody in the market.
I know how much for each of
them it will cost to generate.
So fuel, if I know fuel
price, I can generate
so-called generation stack.
It means the cost of generation
for each of the generators,
for each of the
participants in the market.
The outages will simply
allow me to take out
some of these participants
out of the picture, basically.
So I need to know that, but
that's-- at any given day,
if I know the outages,
I know the fuel prices,
I can construct the cost of
generating for everybody.
So it's close to the bid stack.
It's something that they
will bid-- their cost,
maybe plus some profit.
I don't know what their
profit margins are.
But what I know, I
know the market prices.
I know the options, how
they trade, and so on.
So the bid stack
will, in general,
follow the generation stack.
It will be, more or less,
the same thing, maybe some
added profit requirements.
But I can back these
profit requirements
from the market prices.
That's where my supply-demand
approach and the market
will get together.
I will adjust the generation
stack in such a way,
maybe moving it up and
down in such a way,
that I matched the
prices, and I matched
the option prices, so measured
the volatility of the market.
So now the circle is
completely closed,
if I can succeed in doing that.
Questions?
This is the key.
Well, let's see
if I can do that.
So first I want to-- now if
I manage to do that, then
if I know how to model the
evolution of fuel prices,
if I know how the
outages are modeled,
and I model the demand, then
I can determine how the power
prices will be moving in time.
So power price is the function
of the bid stack and demand,
as you remember.
So if I know the evolution of
the bid stack, the evolution
of the demand, I can determine
the evolution of the power
price-- completely
different approach.
So let's start with the
evolution of the fuel,
with building the fuel model.
Well, I told you that
there is natural gas.
In reality, we have to
model all that stuff.
Because each of them has a
curve because of volatility.
It looks a lot,
but in reality it's
not, because we have
a pretty good idea.
Unlike the power prices
with the spikes and all
this crazy behavior, we
have a pretty good idea
of the behavior of these things,
because they're all storable.
By the way, power
prices are jumping
because of non-storability
of power prices,
because they're not storable.
Because they're non-storable,
you cannot smooth out
the changes in the demand.
Just so you have-- your
action's immediate.
These are all
storable commodities,
so the behavior is
much more regular.
They're much closer, let's
say, to the equity prices.
And so we can use
some standard models.
So from the modeling
point of view,
they are not particularly
difficult to model.
So particularly just natural
gas, heating oil and fuel oil,
just the coal-- just we have
a pretty good understanding
of how these things are modeled.
Outage, well, we take
the standard model from--
and reliability
theory provides us
with a very well-developed
mechanism and apparatus
how to model these things.
I mean, usually we do it
through some kind of Poisson,
or version of Poisson process.
It is very well understood.
There's a lot of
literature on that.
We can model that very easily.
Where do we have the
parameters for these Poissons?
The government
provides us with these.
There's government data.
Sometimes we get it directly
from the power plants.
Everybody keeps track of
the frequency of the outages
and so on and so forth.
Demand-- how will
we model demand?
Well, we'll model demand through
the temperature, typically.
Why temperature?
Because for temperature,
we have a lot of data.
It's statistically
a very stable thing.
So there are many
different approaches
to modeling temperature.
It's up to you.
There's a lot of
literature, so I'm not
going to go into detail.
So we choose something.
We model temperature.
From that, we model the demand.
And it works pretty well.
So now we have-- we modeled
the evolution of temperature,
evolution of demand,
evolution of fuel,
evolution of the outages.
Now we can construct
the generation stack.
So remember, the generation
was this curve, this curve that
was a function of demand,
but also the fraction
of the outages, variable
costs, and so on,
and the fuel, the vector fuels.
And then there's
these parameters alpha
and these alpha
parameters we choose
to match the futures, the
forward curve for the power
prices and all other market
parameters as we need.
So that's how we get-- so
we're matching the market,
and we're matching the kind of
supply and demand formation.
Now, it is very clear
why with this approach,
I can capture spikes without
effort, without any effort.
And the reason is very simple.
This is my-- remember the stack,
my bid stack or generation
stack, whatever.
So for high generation
volumes, it's
becoming more and more
expensive to generate.
And after a certain
time, you've exhausted
all your cheap plants.
You have to go to very,
very expensive plants,
like diesel plants
and so on, which
runs maybe once in a
lifetime, maybe once a year,
twice a year.
And very expensive.
But they determine the price.
They are the ones that
determined the clearing price
at the market.
Now, let's see.
If we are somewhere
here-- this is demand.
Demand is driven by temperature.
Temperature is
typically a normal thing
with maybe mean reversion.
If it goes up, it typically
reverses some mean.
So this is the distribution
of demand around here.
Well, if demand
moves left or right,
up, down, the prices
don't change much.
So that's your normal regime.
But let's assume demand
is somewhere here.
If you are to the left,
the prices are very small.
But the moment you move a
little bit to the right,
your temperature moves a
little bit to the high region.
You immediately spike
into the $1,000 territory.
But remember, temperature's
mean reverting,
so within five, six
days, it comes back.
You go back.
Your price goes from high
levels back to the normal level.
That's your spikes.
You get it completely for free.
And I'll show you right
now a couple of graphs.
One is the actual graph.
The other the simulated
using this approach
for the same market.
So as you can see, this
is the actual price
for that particular period.
These are the prices
that we generate-- just
plain Monte-Carlo simulation.
As you can see, this
can be easily this.
Just from the point of view--
distribution of the spikes
and so on, it's
exactly the same thing.
This is what we were after.
Moreover, I'll
tell you even more.
If I knew the past of
the fuel, then obviously
my approach-- there
are two graphs here.
You cannot distinguish
between them,
because I substituted exactly
the right price of the fuel,
just actual price,
which was historically.
And therefore my price and the
actual price were the same.
So, but the reality, of
course, I don't know the past.
But as I explained to
you, I don't need to know.
I just need to know the
distribution of fuel prices
is correctly captured.
Once I have the correctly
captured distribution
of the fuel prices, I
have, according to this,
correctly captured distribution
of the power prices.
Moreover, so as you can see,
we have a very nice behavior.
Now from the parameter's point
of view, this is the model.
Look at the kurtosis.
This is summers.
Kurtosis of the model and
kurtosis of the empirical
is very, very close.
So the distributions
are very close.
I mean, the skewness
and so on-- it's
a very, very good capturing
of the distribution.
So this approach
works very nicely.
It's completely different
from what you get used to,
but it's really
the one that works.
Moreover, final
benefit-- bonus point--
this is simulated correlation
structure, remember?
And this is the actual
one-- very close.
And the beauty of it is you
don't have-- it's not an input.
It's an output.
I don't ever use the correlation
as an input in my model.
I got it.
I got the distribution of
power, got distribution of fuel,
natural gas, put it all
together, compute correlation
and that's what I've got.
And this means that this is
really a correct approach.
And I don't need
to put it-- I don't
need to look for the
distribution that
has this property.
This property comes
for free, just
as a result of the
completely alternative way
of modeling this thing.
Now, what is the
negative side of this?
The negative side is
it's extremely difficult
to do it and maintain
it, because you
have to maintain the
information of every power plant
and was built, was retired,
and will be built, and so on.
Because you have to
look at the power prices
10 years, 20 years from now.
You have to know what's going
to be there, what kind of stack
you have to forecast.
That's a lot of
information to keep.
I mean, you have to have a big
organization to work on that,
to maintain it, to
build the model.
Because each region in this
country has a different market.
So you have to-- I mean,
it's a massive undertaking.
It takes years.
So it's not like you
can get it from the can.
It's expensive.
So I think that will be a
good point for me to stop.
If you have questions,
please let me know.
Questions?
I think it's music to my ears.
Thank you.